The greatest event in motion picture history!
The Ten Commandments is a drama, history film directed by Cecil B. DeMille.
Escaping death, a Hebrew infant is raised in a
royal household to become a prince.
Upon discovery of his true heritage, Moses embarks on a personal quest to
reclaim his destiny as the leader and liberator of the Hebrew people.
Moses, played by Charlton Heston.
Rameses, played by Yul Brynner.
Nefretiri, played by Anne Baxter.
Dathan, played by Edward G. Robinson.
Sephora, played by Yvonne De Carlo.
Lilia, played by Debra Paget.
The Ten Commandments is a 1956 American epic biblical drama
film produced, directed, and narrated by Cecil B.
DeMille, shot in VistaVision (color by Technicolor),
and released by Paramount Pictures.
Based on the Bible's Book of Exodus and other sources, it dramatizes the story of the life of Moses, an adopted Egyptian prince who becomes the deliverer of
his real brethren, the enslaved Hebrews, and thereafter leads the Exodus to Mount Sinai, where he receives, from God, the Ten Commandments.
The film stars Charlton Heston in the lead role, Yul Brynner as
Rameses, Anne Baxter as Nefretiri, Edward G.
Robinson as Dathan, Yvonne De Carlo as Sephora, Debra Paget as Lilia, and John Derek as Joshua; and features Sir Cedric Hardwicke as
Sethi I, Nina Foch as Bithiah, Martha Scott as Yochabel, Judith Anderson as Memnet, and Vincent Price as Baka, among others.
First announced in 1952, The Ten Commandments is a remake of the
prologue of DeMille's 1923 silent film of the same title.
Four screenwriters, three art directors, and five
costume designers worked on the film.
In 1954, it was filmed on location in Egypt, Mount Sinai, and the Sinai Peninsula,
featuring one of the largest exterior sets ever created for a motion picture.
In 1955, the interior sets were constructed on
Paramount's Hollywood soundstages.
The original roadshow version included an onscreen introduction by DeMille and was released to cinemas in the United
States on November 8, 1956, and, at the time of its release, was the most expensive film ever made.
It was DeMille's most successful work, his first widescreen film, his fourth biblical
production, and his final directorial effort before his death in 1959.
In 1957, the film was nominated for seven Academy Awards, including Best
Picture, winning the Academy Award for Best Visual Effects (John P.
Fulton, A.S.C.).
DeMille won the Foreign Language Press Film
Critics Circle Award for Best Director.
Charlton Heston was nominated for a Golden Globe Award for Best
Performance by an Actor in a Motion Picture (Drama).
Yul Brynner won the National Board of Review Award for Best Actor.
Heston, Anne Baxter, and Yvonne De Carlo won Laurel Awards for Best Dramatic Actor, 5th
Best Dramatic Actress, and 3rd Best Supporting Actress, respectively.
It is also one of the most financially successful films ever made, grossing approximately $122.7 million at the box office during
its initial release; it was the most successful film of 1956 and the second-highest-grossing film of the decade.
According to Guinness World Records, in terms of theatrical exhibition, it is the eighth most
successful film of all-time when the box office gross is adjusted for inflation.
In 1999, the film was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the
Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
In June 2008, the American Film Institute revealed its "Ten Top Ten"—the best ten films in ten
American film genres—after polling over 1,500 people from the creative community.
The film was listed as the tenth best film in the epic genre.
The film has aired annually on U.S.
network television in prime time during the Passover/Easter season since 1973.
The film explores themes of egypt, israel, moses,
ten commandments, christianity.
The tone is emotional.